Guide to the Stanford Eating Clubs Records SC1054
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Eating Clubs records
1920-2000
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Eating Clubs
SC1054
1.99 megabyte(s)
8.25 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
The materials consist of meeting minutes, reports, financial ledgers, photographs, ephemera, and newsletters documenting the activities of the Stanford Eating Clubs.
Access to Collection
Open for research use.
Acquisition Information
The materials were a gift of Nick Peters, 2011 and 2012 & Helen Holmes Peak, 2016.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of meeting minutes, reports, financial ledgers, photographs, ephemera, and newsletters documenting the activities of the Stanford Eating Clubs.
Biographical / Historical
The Stanford Eating Clubs, also known as the Toyon Eating Clubs, were founded in 1892, making them the oldest student managed group on the Stanford University campus. They were originally formed by congenial bands of like-minded men who were unhappy with the food and service offered by the University-sponsored Stanford Inn. Even before the first Club was formed, some students were eating at the mess hall of "The Camp," a crude barrack community built on the site of the student union. It was here, in 1894, that the first Club — Brookfarm Eating Club — was founded. Brookfarm lasted only one year, but it was a beginning, and the "eating club" concept continued to grow. Other co-operative eating groups were formed at "The Camp" and in nearby Palo Alto and Mayfield (now the California Avenue area of Palo Alto). "The Camp" was closed in 1902, but it didn't dampen the Club spirit, and the leading students of those days continued to trek off campus three times a day for their meals. In 1907 several of the Clubs with houses in College Terrace — Snell, Welakahao, Marchmount, and Entre Nous — banded together to form the Terrace Club. With one exception, these Clubs all subsequently disbanded. Entre Nous, however, founded in 1901, became the first of the seven present Clubs. The name was changed to Los Arcos in 1922. In 1909, Breakers Club was organized in a small cottage on Stanford Avenue near its intersection with Escondido Road. Breakers remained there for one year before moving to the Frenchman's House, located on Escondido Road. El Campo and El Toro were also founded in these early years of the century. In the fall of 1912, the "Little Quad" was completed and Breakers, El Campo, and El Toro moved into this small U-shaped building next to Encina Hall near the present Club building.
By the 1950s, the all-male Eating Clubs had become an alternative to the fraternity system. The eating clubs were abolished in 2009-2010. A new dining hall, "Linx," was established in favor of the eating clubs, and Toyon students are part of the campus meal plan system.
Stanford University -- Eating clubs.; College students.; Students -- Societies, etc.; Student activities.; Education -- Societies, etc.; Stanford Eating Clubs
- Minutes, 1939-1952 (Box 1)
- Report of the Interclub Manager, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
- El Cuadro, Annaul Report of the Business Manager, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
- El Tigre Club ledger, 1952-1957 (Box 1)
- Minutes, 1957-1960 (Box 1)
- Report of the Interclub Manger, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
- President's Report, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
- General Manger's log book, 1983 (Box 1)
- 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 101st Anniversary, 1995 Aug (Box 2, Folder 2)
- El Toro newsletter, 1956-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Articles of Incorporation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Articles, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Breakers (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Clubs (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Current status of Eating Clubs, 2000 Oct 21 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Eating Clubs, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- El Toro constitution (Box 2, Folder 10)
- El Campo (Box 2, Folder 11)
- El Capitan (Box 2, Folder 12)
- El Cuadro (Box 2, Folder 13)
- El Tigre (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Eating Clubs History (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Los Arcos (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Photographs (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Recipes/Stories (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
- Songs (Box 2, Folder 20)
- The Stanford Clubs, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- "The Stanford Eating Clubs: The First 100 Years" (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
- El Toro member journal, check register, receipts (Box 3)
- El Toro Club ledger, circa 1922-1943 (Box 3)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes minutes, member ship lists, expenses, etc.
- Stanford Eating Clubs general ledger, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  Includes assets, liabilities, funds, income, expenses, etc.
- El Cuadro photograph album, circa 1920s-1961 (Box 4)
- Loose scrapbook and photograph album pages (Box 5)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2013-003
  - Two exhibit posters with text and photographs about history of Stanford Eating Clubs, co-authored by Matt Pozos and Nick Peters, 1995 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2013-015
  This accession contains the Stanford Eating Clubs Alumni roster as well as recipes and stories contributed by alumni.
  - SEC Alum Master List, 2 computer media (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stanford Eating Clubs Alumni Contacts (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stanford Eating Clubs Alumni Contacts (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2015-085
  - El Capitan Sponge List, 1961 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2017-063
  - Administrative records, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - El Cuadro photographs, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Eating club plates (2 El Campo, 1 El Cuadro) (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2018-103
  - Stanford '63 Eating Clubs, 1963 (Box 1)